ILGWU Education Department, Fannia Cohn Papers on Microfilm 5780/049 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Education Department, Fannia Cohn Papers on Microfilm
1918-1962
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cohn, Fannia M. (Fannia Mary), 1885-
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/049 mf
1 cubic feet
9 microfilm reels
Articles, reprints, pamphlets, correspondence, photographs, microfilm.
The collection contains correspondence, subject files, speeches, articles, photographs, and programs from Fannia Cohn's term as Executive Secretary of the ILGWU Education Department on microfilm.
8230219
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kathryn Dowgiewicz, February 07, 2013
Biographical / Historical
Founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States, the ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. In 1995, the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) to form the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE).
Biographical / Historical
Fannia Cohn was born in Minsk in the late 1880s (there is disagreement as to the exact year). She emigrated to the U.S. in 1904 and began working in a New York garment factory in 1905. She joined the ILGWU in 1909 and quickly emerged as a skilled leader and organizer. She was the first woman vice-president of the ILGWU and in 1918 became Executive Secretary of the Education Department, a position she held until her retirement in 1961. She played a significant role in worker education and was a co-founder of both the Workers' Education Bureau and the Brookwood Labor College. She died in 1962 in New York City.
Biographical / Historical
Local union's of the ILGWU established and maintained robust, ambitious educational departments early on in the international's history. As these groups grew in size and scope, the international office sought to coordinate and centralize educational programming for the union's members, culminating in the formation of the Educational Department in 1918.
The department's programming included courses at the Workers' University at the Washington Irving High School in New York City, lectures at Unity Centers and Unity Houses in the northeastern United States, and other events. The educational offerings of the International's Education Department were varied, as had been the education departments of the local unions, and included not only classes in labor studies but also courses in languages, music, and the arts. The ILGWU's 1937 musical "Pins and Needles" exemplified the diversity of the union's programs.
Directors of the Education Department, especially Fannia Cohn and Mark Starr, wrote extensively on the ILGWU's programs and worker education in general. Longtime director Gus Tyler not only directed the department, but also served as the ILGWU's on-staff scholar. In later years, the Education Department went beyond collaborating with other education organizations and arranging in-house programs to also supporting post-secondary education for union members and their families.
Scope and Contents
The Education Department records document activities across the entire period of the department's existence, with the bulk of the records covering the 1970s and 1990s. It contains papers from directors of the Education Department: Fannia Cohn, Mark Starr, Gus Tyler, and Kitty Krupat.
The earliest documentation of the department's work is found in the Fannia Cohn papers (5780/049, 5780/049 P); these contain correspondence, subject files, speeches, photographs, and printed material from her work as director of the Educational Department. A microfilm copy of the Fannia Cohn papers held at the New York Public Library (5998 mf) complements the Kheel Center's holdings. Documentation of the work of another longtime leader of the Education Department, Mark Starr, is contained in these records (5780/166, 5780/166 PUBS), as well as in a related collection from Starr on worker education programs (5243).
Documentation of the work of Gus Tyler, who led the merged Education and Political Department after Mark Starr's retirement in 1960, is also contained in the ILGWU records (5780/052, 5780/088, 5780/096). Tyler's papers are complemented by those of Assistant Director Jasper Peyton (5780/086) and Special Projects Coordinator Beverly Shulman (5780/106). These collections contain routine correspondence and memoranda, reports, materials relating to training institutes, seminars, and conferences, and printed material.
The papers of Kitty Krupat, who was serving as Education Director at the time of the ILGWU/ACTWU merger in 1995, constitute the entirety of Education Department records from the 1990s. They include correspondence, memoranda, reports, and financial records relating to the ILGWU's independent and collaborative education projects, including the Worker-Family Education Program, the Joint Union-University Committee on Labor Education, and the Consortium for Worker Education, as well as numerous trainings, conferences, and seminars. Also included in the files are materials from local unions and regional departments of the ILGWU, files on the Internationals' conventions, and reports to the General Executive Board.
The Fannia Cohn papers (5780/049) contain correspondence, subject files, speeches, articles, photographs, and programs from Fannia Cohn's term as Executive Secretary of the ILGWU Education Department. The materials in Series I are primarily letters between Cohn and various individuals pertaining to trade union matters in general and the ILGWU in particular. Included in the series are programs for lectures, concerts, museum visits and tours of New York City that were offered to ILGWU members and others as part of the Education Department's activities. Series II consists of bulletins, articles, lectures and course outlines. Most of these materials were written by Cohn herself or were prepared under her direction for use at the union's Unity Centers and at the Workers' University. A number of articles are by Mark Starr. There are also lectures by Charles A. Beard; Robert Brure; Babette Deutsch; Paul H. Douglas; Harry Laidler; A.J. Muste; Grace Scribner; Alexander Trachtenberg; Carl Van Doren; and Theresa Wolfson, among others. Significant individuals represented in the collection include David Dubinsky, Samuel Gompers, Morris Sigman ,Rose Pesotta, and H.G. Wells. Organizations include the Education Department of the ILGWU, the Brookwood Labor College, the AFL, Pioneer Youth of America, the Rand School of Social Science, and Unity House.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780/106: ILGWU. Education Department. Beverly Shulman papers 5780/138: ILGWU. Education Department. Kitty Krupat papers 5780/166: ILGWU. Education Department records 5780/166 PUBS: ILGWU. Education Department publications 5780/086: ILGWU. Education Department. Jasper Peyton papers 5780/049: ILGWU. Education Department. Fannia Cohn papers 5780/049 P: ILGWU. Education Department. Fannia Cohn photographs
Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States; Labor unions -- Officials and employees; Labor movement.; Labor movement -- United States; Labor unions; Labor unions -- United States; Labor unions and education -- United States; Working class -- Education -- United States; Beard, Charles A.(Charles Austin), 1874-1948.; Brue`re, Robert W.(Robert Walter), 1876-1964.; Deutsch, Babette, 1895-; Douglas, Paul Howard, 1892-; Dubinsky, David, 1892-1982.; Gompers, Samuel, 1850-1924.; Laidler, Harry Wellington, 1884-1970.; Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967.; Scribner, Grace, 1882- 1922.; Sigman, Morris, 1880-1931.; Starr, Mark, 1894-; Trachtenberg, Alexander.; Van Doren, Carl, 1885- 1950.; Wells, H. G.(Herbert George), 1866-1946.; Wolfson, Theresa, 1897-1972.; American Federation of Labor; Brookwood Labor College (Katonah, N.Y.); International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Educational Dept; Pioneer Youth of America; Rand School of Social Science
8230219
- A, 1921-1959; 1 (Reel 2)
- Agricultural Dept., U.S., 1938; 2 (Reel 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes correspondence with Resettlement and Farm Security Administrations with Arch A. Mercey.
- American Federation of Labor, 1918-1954; 3 (Reel 2)
  Includes correspondence with Samuel Gompers & C. Thorne.
- American Labor Education Service, Inc. (formerly the Affiliated School for Workers), 1936-1941; 4 (Reel 2)
- B, 1921-1957; 5 (Reel 2)
- Balabanoff, Angelica, 1938-1943; 6 (Reel 2)
  1938, 1943
- Barnum, Gertz, 1913-1945; 7 (Reel 2)
  1913, 1945
- Beard, Charles A., 1920-1948; 8 (Reel 2)
- Beard, Mary, 1924-1928; 9 (Reel 2)
- Brameld, Theodore, 1940-1941; 10 (Reel 2)
- Brookwood Labor Colleges, 1921-1935; 11 (Reel 2)
- C, 1921-1960; 12 (Reel 2)
- Chicago Joint, 1923-1947; 13 (Reel 2)
  1923, 1947
- Columbia University, 1926-1959; 14 (Reel 2)
  1926, 1942-1959. Includes correspondence with Harry J. Carman (dean) & William F. Russell.
- D, 1936-1958; 15 (Reel 2)
- Dubinsky, David, 1926-1950; 16 (Reel 2)
- E, 1922-1953; 17 (Reel 2)
  1922, 1939-1953
- Education, 1934-1945; 18 (Reel 2)
  Includes Liaison for International Education and Conference on the Educational and Cultural Organization of the United Nations.
- Education Committee, ILGWU, 1954; 19 (Reel 2)
  Fannia Cohn to Julius Hochman (chairman) outlining educational activities of Union.
- England, 1924-1954; 20 (Reel 2)
  Includes correspondence with The Labor Party, Ellen Wilkinson, Ernest Bevin and Morgan Phillips & ltr. from H.G. Wells.
- F, 1921-1957; 21 (Reel 2)
  Includes correspondence with Mollie Friedman.
- Form Letters, 1935-1951; 1 (Reel 3)
  1935-1936, 1941-1951
- Forsberg, Allen B., 1922; 2 (Reel 3)
- Frey, John P., 1922-1942; 3 (Reel 3)
  1922-1928, 1942
- Frish, Evelyn, 1930-1931; 4 (Reel 3)
- G, 1922-1956; 5 (Reel 3)
- Greetings, 1950-1959; 6 (Reel 3)
  1950s
- H, 1921-1959; 7 (Reel 3)
- History of the ILGWU, partial manuscript, no author, no date., 8 (Reel 3)
- I, 1939-1952; 9 (Reel 3)
  Includes Isaacs, Stanley M., 1939, 1943.
- J, 1921-1960; 10 (Reel 3)
  1921, 1940-1960
- Justice, 1937-1959; 11 (Reel 3)
  Announcements of programs and related articles.
- K, 1926-1957; 12 (Reel 3)
  1926, 1940-1957
- L, 1921-1957; 13 (Reel 3)
  Includes correspondence with Lewis Lorwin (Louis Levine).
- Labor Department, U.S., 1921-1953; 14 (Reel 3)
  1921, 1933-1953
- Life and Labor, 1921; 15 (Reel 3)
  (Publ. by Women's Trade Union League) Corres.
- Locals and Union Affiliates, 1922-1959; 16 (Reel 3)
- Local 25, 1919-1925; 17 (Reel 3)
  Includes correspondence with Elsie Gluck (education dir.).
- Local 38, N.Y.C., 1930-1931; 18 (Reel 3)
  Strike. Includes corres. of the Citizens' Emergency Committee is behalf of the striking ladies' Tailors and custom dressmakers of the Fifth Avenue Shops.
- Local 91, N.Y.C., 1924-1939; 19 (Reel 3)
  1924-1930s
- Local 178, 1937; 20 (Reel 3)
  May-June 1937, Education Dept. program.
- M, 1933-1960; 21 (Reel 3)
- Miller (jr.), Spencer, 1926-1955; 22 (Reel 3)
  1926-1927, 1941-1955
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1920-1959; 1 (Reel 5)
  1920s-1950s
- Miscellaneous Items. (Union and non-Union), 2 (Reel 5)
- N, 1922-1958; 3 (Reel 5)
- O, 1946-1960; 4 (Reel 5)
- Organization of American States. Pan American Union, 1949-1950; 5 (Reel 5)
- P, 1922-1947; 6 (Reel 5)
  Includes correspondence with Rose Pesotta.
- Panel Discussions, General Matters, 1940-1959; 7 (Reel 5)
  1940s-1950s
- Panel Discussions, 1942-1946; 8 (Reel 5)
- Panel Discussions, 1947-1948; 9 (Reel 5)
- Panel Discussions, 1949-1952; 10 (Reel 5)
- Panel Discussions, 1953; 11 (Reel 5)
- Panel Discussions, 1953-1955; 12 (Reel 5)
- Perlman, Selig, 1929-1959; 13 (Reel 5)
- Pioneer Youth of America, 1926-1933; 14 (Reel 5)
- Pioneer Youth of America, 1934-1938; 15 (Reel 5)
- Pioneer Youth of America, 1939-1960; 16 (Reel 5)
- Programs. Education programs from various locals., 1 (Reel 8)
- Programs, 1930-1939; 2 (Reel 8)
  1930s Education Department announcement of coming events and programs.
- Programs, 1940-1942; 3 (Reel 8)
- Programs, 1943-1946; 4 (Reel 8)
- Programs, 1948; 5 (Reel 8)
- Programs, 1949; 6 (Reel 8)
- Programs, 1950-1951; 7 (Reel 8)
- Programs, 1953-1961; 8 (Reel 8)
- R, 1921-1959; 9 (Reel 8)
  1921, 1937-1959
- Rand School of Social Science, 1930-1953; 10 (Reel 8)
  1930, 1953
- Reports and articles on Education, 1940-1959; 11 (Reel 8)
- Rutgers University, 1941-1950; 12 (Reel 8)
  1941, 1947-1950
- S, 1924-1959; 13 (Reel 8)
- Sigman, Morris, 1924; 14 (Reel 8)
- Strikes, 1924-1932; 15 (Reel 8)
  1924, 1930, 1932
- T, 1921-1959; 16 (Reel 8)
  1921, 1935-1959
- Training Institute, 1958; 17 (Reel 8)
- U, 1939-1954; 18 (Reel 8)
- Unemployment Insurance, 1932; 19 (Reel 8)
- United Nations, 1949-1962; 20 (Reel 8)
  Visits of Union members to UN.
- United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organizations (UNESCO), 1945-1952; 21 (Reel 8)
- Unity Centers, 1920-1922; 22 (Reel 8)
- Unity House, 1921-1933; 1 (Reel 10)
  Includes correspondence re lectures held at Unity House.
- Unity House, 1937-1938; 2 (Reel 10)
- V, 1918-1953; 3 (Reel 10)
  1918, 1934-1953
- Wisconsin University at Madison, School for Workers, 1938-1959; 4 (Reel 10)
- Wolfson, Theresa, 1922-1931; 5 (Reel 10)
- Women's Trade Union League, 1921-1949; 6 (Reel 10)
  Workers' Defense League, 1921
- Workers Education Bureau of America, 1921-1943; 7 (Reel 10)
  1921, 1923, 1925, 1929, 1938-1943. Includes correspondence, minutes and reports.
- Workers Education Bureau of America, 1943-1958; 8 (Reel 10)
- Works Progress Administration. Federal Theatre Projects., 1936-1939; 9 (Reel 10)
- Y-Z, 1943-1953; 10 (Reel 10)
  1943, 1947, 1953
- At Your Service, 1946-1949; 11 (Reel 10)
  Bulletin.
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 1 of 6], 12 (Reel 10)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 2 of 6], 13 (Reel 10)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 3 of 6], 14 (Reel 10)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 4 of 6], 15 (Reel 10)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 5 of 6], 16 (Reel 10)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Notes for speeches, statements, articles and ltrs. [folder 6 of 6], 1 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, A-C., 2 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, D-I., 3 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, L., 4 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, M-N., 5 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, 0., 6 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, P., 7 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, R-S., 8 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, T-U., 9 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, W-WI., 10 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, WO-Z. [folder 1 of 2], 11 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Articles, WO-Z. [folder 2 of 2], 12 (Reel 11)
- Cohn, Fannia M. Convention speeches, 1937-1959; 13 (Reel 11)
- In Union There Is Strength (a play), 1937; 14 (Reel 11)
  One-act play by Fannia M. Cohn & Irwin Swerdlow, 3rd ed.
- Lecture Series, 1921-1925; 15 (Reel 11)
  Announcement of Courses given at Workers University.
- Lecture Series, 1921-1922; 16 (Reel 11)
  Attendance records.
- Lecture Series, 1921-1926; 17 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Ardzrooni, Leon and (Albrecht, Arthur E.)., 18 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Ayres, C.E., 19 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Bauer, Marian., 20 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Beard, Charles A., 21 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Boone, Gladys., 22 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Branham, Lucy., 23 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Brissenden, Paul F., 24 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Bruere, Robert., 25 (Reel 11)
- Lecture Series. Calhoun, A. W., 1 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Carman, Harry J. [folder 1 of 2], 2 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Carman, Harry J. [folder 2 of 2], 3 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Carr, Michael., 4 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Daniels, Margaret., 5 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Deutsch, Babette., 6 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Douglas, Paul H., 7 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Fichandler, Alexander., 8 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Gadsby, Margaret; Glassberg, Benjamin; Goodrich, Carter L., 9 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Holloway, Emory., 10 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Kennan, Ellen A., 11 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Kopland, Sylvia., 12 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Kornhauser, Arthur W., 13 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Laidler, Harry W., 14 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Lehrer, Leib., 15 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Levin, Max., 16 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Lieberman, Elias., 17 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Lyon, John H., 18 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Marx, Olga., 19 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Mautner, B.H., 20 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Melvin, F.J., 21 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Meyers, J., 22 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Miller (jr.), Spencer., 23 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Muste, A.J., 24 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Overstreet, Harry., 25 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Saposs, David J., 26 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Scribner, Grace., 27 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Selikman, Benjamin; Soule, George., 28 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Sherry, Harry., 29 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Stair, Bird., 30 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Stolberg, Benjamin., 31 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Stopler, B.J.R., 32 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Trachtenberg, Alexander., 33 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Van Doren, Carl., 34 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Weinzweig, Max., 35 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Wilbert, A.L., 36 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Wolfson, Theresa., 37 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Wolman, Leo., 38 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Zimand Savel., 39 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Misc. course outlines., 40 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Misc. course outlines., 41 (Reel 13)
- Lecture Series. Programs, 1920-1926; 42 (Reel 13)
- New Members' Classes. Lessons II and III., 43 (Reel 13)
- Officers Qualification Course, 1952; 44 (Reel 13)
  Syllabus for the six lessons.
- Plays, Union., 45 (Reel 13)
- Plays, Union., 1 (Reel 15)
- Printed Material from Education Dept. Misc., 2 (Reel 15)
- Printed Material from Education Dept. Misc., 3 (Reel 15)
- Reports of Education Department, 1922-1940; 4 (Reel 15)
- Reports of Education Department, 1941-1956; 5 (Reel 15)
- Songs. Union and local affiliates., 6 (Reel 15)
- Songs. Union and local affiliates., 7 (Reel 15)
- Songs. Union and local affiliates., 8 (Reel 15)
- Songs. Union and local affiliates., 9 (Reel 15)
  Corres.
- Mark Starr, 1942-1943; 1 (Reel 18)
- Starr, Mark. Articles, arranged alphabetically by title, A-0., 2 (Reel 18)
- Starr, Mark. Articles, P-Z., 3 (Reel 18)
- Structure and government of the ILGWU, 1934; 4 (Reel 18)
  Article
- Studies. Union and Government Efforts to Regulate Wages and Hours in the Illinois Women's Cotton Garment Industry, 1939-1941; 5 (Reel 18)
  1939, 1941. Garment Workers of Other Lands by Abe S. Weiss, 1941.
- Training-for-Trade-Union-Service, 1935-1941; 6 (Reel 18)
- Training-For-Trade-Union-Service, 1946-1947; 7 (Reel 18)
- Training-For-Trade-Union-Service, 1946-1947; 8 (Reel 18)
- Trends and Prospects in the Women's Garment Industry, 1940-1956; 9 (Reel 18)
  GEB Reports to Convention.
- Workers' Education, 1926-1941; 10 (Reel 18)
  1926, 1929, 1935, 1941A quarterly journal of American Workers' Education.
- Workers Education Bureau of America, 1940-1953; 11 (Reel 18)
  Includes newsletters.